Asa Barth-Maron (He/Him)

asabarthmaron@gmail.com | Cambridge, MA | +1 (917) 647-7235 asabarthmaron.github.io

Summary

I am a Data Scientist at Neumora Therapeutics, with interdisciplinary expertise in machine learning, biochemistry, drug development, and neuroscience. I am interested in developing and applying methods for learning representations and generating insight from biological data for drug discovery.

Key Skills

Technical: Python, PyTorch, MLflow, Scikit-learn, SciPy/NumPy/Pandas, RDKit, CellProfiler,

MATLAB, R, AWS, LSF, Slurm.

Quantitative: Deep Learning, Digital Signal Processing, Statistical Analysis, Representation Learning

Experimental Design, Interdisciplinary communication, Microscopy, Neurophysiology. Scientific:

Professional Experience

Data Scientist II, Neumora Therapeutics

2022 - Present

- Developed single-cell segmentation and feature extraction pipelines. Sole person responsible for all microscopy data pipelines and analyses. Interfaced closely with lab scientists.
- Implemented VAEs to generate insights from unbiased cellular morphology datasets.
- Conducted experiments for molecular property prediction using latest state-of-the-art graph neural networks and molecular representation learning (ongoing).

Graduate Researcher. Harvard Medical School, Department of Neurobiology

2015 - 2022

- Research on how network architectures enable distinct computations during sensory encoding.
- Discovered neuron populations that implement different forms of normalization.
- Developed dynamical systems and population activity decoding models.
- Hired, trained, mentored over 20 research assistants. Managed teams of 3-5.

Graduate Researcher. Harvard Medical School, Department of Neurobiology

2015

Developed biologically realistic CNNs to model mid-size visual feature detection in primate visual cortex area V4. NVIDIA hardware grant recipient.

Research Assistant. Harvard Medical School, Department of Neurobiology

2012 - 2014

Characterized the biochemistry of a signaling protein involved in synapse development.

Education

Harvard University

Boston, MA

Ph.D. in Neuroscience, Distinction in Computational Neuroscience

February, 2022

- NIH Kirschstein-NRSA Fellow
- Relevant Courses: Probability Theory, Machine Learning, Statistical Machine Learning

Lehigh University

Bethlehem, PA

B.S. in Neuroscience

January, 2013

Teaching Fellow, Intro. to Computational Neuroscience

2021

 Topics included deep learning, reinforcement learning, recurrent neural networks, neural encoding and decoding, generalized linear models, and dynamical systems analysis.

Teaching Fellow, Boot Camp in Quantitative Methods

2015, 2019

Taught programming fundamentals and data analysis methods in MATLAB.

EEG Motor Imagery, personal project

 Implemented the Filter Bank Common Spatial Pattern (FBCSP) algorithm from scratch to classify imagined movements.

Distributed high-performance computing

2014 - 2022

Ran large-scale models and analyses on the LSF-managed cluster at Harvard Medical School.

Large-Scale Connectomics Project Management

2015 - 2018

Managed DVID backend server and NeuTu clients for large-scale reconstruction effort.

Publications & Presentations

Publications

- Barth-Maron A., D'Alessandro I., Wilson R.I. (2023). Interactions between specialized gain control mechanisms in olfactory processing. Current Biology 33 (23), 5109-5120. e7
- **Barth-Maron A.** (2022). Interneuron diversity in the Drosophila antennal lobe promotes computational flexibility and adaptive coding properties. **Harvard University**, 2022. 29209804.
- Schlegel, P., Bates, A.S., Stürner, T., Jagannathan, S.R., Drummond, N., Hsu, J., Serratosa Capdevila, L., Javier, A., Marin, E.C., Barth-Maron, A., et al. (2021). Information flow, cell types and stereotypy in a full olfactory connectome. eLife 10, e66018.
- Guo W., Clause A.R., Barth-Maron A., Polley D.B. (2018) A Corticothalamic Circuit for Dynamic Switching between Feature Detection and Discrimination. Neuron, Volume 95, Issue 1, 180-194.e5
- Veeramah K.R., Johnstone L, Karafet T.M., Wolfe D., Sprissler R., Salogiannis J., Barth-Maron A., Greenberg M.E., Pazzi M., Restifo L.L., Talwar D., Erickson R.P., Hammer M.F. (2013) Exome sequencing reveals new causal mutations in children with epileptic encephalopathies. Epilepsia 54(7): 1270-1281.

Conferences & Seminars

- Barth-Maron A., Horne J.A., Katz W.T., Plaza S.M., Scheffer L.K., D'Alessandro I., Meinertzhagen I.A., Lee W.A., Wilson R.I. (2019) What is the role of interneuron diversity in the Drosophila antennal lobe? Neurobiology of Drosophila, Cold Spring Harbor. (poster)
- Barth-Maron A., Horne J.A., Katz W.T., Plaza S.M., Scheffer L.K., D'Alessandro I., Meinertzhagen I.A., Lee W.A., Wilson R.I. (2018) What is the role of interneuron diversity in the Drosophila antennal lobe? Harvard Medical School, Department of Neurobiology Friday Seminar Series. (talk)
- Guo W., Clause A.R., Barth-Maron A., Shinn-Cunningham B.G., Polley D.B. (2015) Layer 6
 corticothalamic neurons modulate the Gain and Selectivity of columnar sound processing. Society for
 Neuroscience, Annual Meeting Abstract 596.13/J26. (poster)